Guide to the John Stuart Mill Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Stuart Mill papers
1812-1888
MS 350
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
(5 boxes)
Chiefly correspondence, to or from Mill. Of the 237 letters by Mill, 131 are to his wife, Harriet Hardy Taylor Mill. Twenty-four letters are from Helen Taylor, Mrs. Mill's daughter. In addition there are two volumes with drafts of letters by Mill written between 1851 and 1858 to a variety of recipients. Notable correspondents in the collection are John Austin, Jeremy Bentham, Augustus De Morgan, Isabella Beecher Hooker, George Grote, John Sterling and Edward Livingston Youmans. Other manuscript material includes four pages of his autobiography (dated 1861), his journal of a walking tour through Berkshire, Buckinghamshire and Surrey (1828) and several undated fragments, including several pages of medical advice to an unnamed person.
Mill, John Stuart, 1806-1873
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired through purchase and gift, 1944-1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John Stuart Mill, philosopher, and the eldest son of James Mill (1773 - l836), a utilitarian philosopher, was born in Pentonville, London, on May 20, 1806. Mill was sternly educated by his father in Greek, Latin, and arithmetic by his eighth year. At twelve years, he began studying logic, including Aristotle and Hobbes. In May 1820, he became a serious scholar of French, while living with Sir Samuel Bentham (1757 - 1831) in France.
In 1822, Mill went to work for the East India Company, a position that gave him much time for study and discussion. He began writing for newspapers by 1823, his first article being a letter in the Traveller.
Mill suffered a mental breakdown in 1836, which caused evaluation of the utilitarian philosophy and the beginning of his great works. A System of Logic, Ratiocinative and Inductive appeared in two volumes in l843.
In 1830, Mill met Mrs. Harriet Taylor (1807 - 1858), who was at the time married; however, Mr. Taylor died in 1849; and in 1851, J. Mill and Harriet Taylor were married. Both were ill during the majority of their marriage, and Mrs. Mill died of lung congestion in Avignon, 1858. Mill returned to intellectual pursuits and politics; he served Parliament in 1865, but was defeated in 1868. Mill died May 8, 1873, in Avignon.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Mill, Hardy, and Taylor families, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Scope and Contents
The John Stuart Mill Collection extends from 1812 - 1888, with around 425 items, mainly correspondence to or from John Stuart Mill. There are 237 letters by Mill, 131 of which are to his wife, Harriet (Hardy) Taylor Mill. Twenty-four letters are from Helen Taylor (1831 - 1907), Mrs. Mill's daughter.
The collection contains letters from Jeremy Bentham (1748 - 1832) to James Mill and John Stuart Mill. Bentham's philosophy was very influential upon James Mill and John Stuart Mill in his early years.
Letters to or from John Sterling (1806 - 1844), John Austin (1790 1859), Augustus DeMorgan (1806 - 1871), Edward Livingston Youmans (1806 - 1873), Herbert Spencer (1820 - 1903), and George Grote (1794 - 1871) are important to the collection. George Grote's friendship is particularly vital to Mill's own thought. The Grote - Mill letters contain discussion of Platonic thought in conjunction with Aristotle, Socrates, and Xanophon. Augutus DeMorgan's letters contain discussions of Plato and Comte.
Of the female correspondents, an Isabella Beecher Hooker (1822 - 1907) letter of August 10, l869, covers Mill's book, The Subjection of Women, as well as some Hooker thoughts on woman suffrage.
Mill's own copious letters to Harriet give a thorough account of their, relationship and the overpowering influence which she held on his life. The subject is well covered in F. A. Hayek's work, John Stuart Mill and Harriet Taylor. The friendship was ostensibly one of equality, as reflected in Mill's letters contained in the collection.
The John Stuart Mill Collection reveals much of Mill's personal life and an ample amount of his published philosophy. Anyone interested in philosophy as it developed in the nineteenth century would find the Mill correspondence valuable.
Appendix: Correspondents
Adams, Sarah Fuller (Flower) (1805 - 1848)
Amberley, John Russell, Viscount, (1842 - 1878)
American and Continental Literary Agency
Argyll, George Douglas Campbell, Eighth Duke, (1823 - 1900)
Arnold, Sir Edwin, (1832 - 1904)
Ashburton, William Bingham Baring, Second Baron, (1799 - 1864)
Austin, John, (1790 - 1859)
Avignon, France
Baer, Constantino
Bain, Alexander, (1806 - 1873)
Barnard, James Munson, (1819 - 1904)
Beal, James
Beggs, Thomas
Bentham, Jeremy, (1748 - 1832)
Bernays, Leopold John, (1820 - 1882)
Bevans, John
Bigot, Mary Healy
Cairnes, Eliza Charlotte (Alexander)
Cairnes, John Elliot
Campbell, Alexander,
Cazelles, Emile Honore, (1831 - )
Cazelles, Marie Anne Clotilde (Peyron)
Chapman, Dr. John (1822 - 1894)
Chape, Auguste Joanny
Christie, William Dougal (1816 - l874)
Colet, Madame Louise
Cowper, Thomas A.
DeMorgan Augustus (1806 - 1871)
Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Fourteenth Earl, (1799 - 1869)
Dilke, Sir Charles Vlentworth (1843 - 1911)
Duffy, charles Garvari, (1816 - 1903)
Fawcett, Dame Mellicent (Garett), (1847 - 1929)
Fawcett, Henry, (1833 - 1884)
Flower, Eliza, (1803 - 1846)
Fox, Eliza (Florance)
Fox, William Johnson, (1786 - 1864)
Godwin, Parke, (1816 - 1901)
Graham, William, (1839 - 1911)
Grant, Horace
Grey, Henry George, Third Earl, (1802 - 1894)
Grote, George, (1794 - 1871)
Gurney, Dr. H. Cecil
Hardy, Arthur
Hare, Eleanor Bowes (Benson)
Hare, Thomas (1806 - 1891)
Harrison, Frederick, (1831 - 1923)
Helps, Sir Arthur, (1813 - 1875)
Herbert, Auberon Edward William Malyneux, (1838 - 1906)
Herschel, Sir John Frederick William, (1792 - 1871)
Hobart, Vere Henry Hobart, Baron, (1818 - 187,)
Hooker, Isabella Beecher, (1822 - 1907)
Howitt, Mary Botham, (1799 - 1888)
Huth, Augusta LouisA Sophia (Westenholz), ( - 1889)
Irvine, Alexander, (1793 - 1873)
Leslie, Thomas Edward Cliffe, (1827? - 1882)
Ley, William
Linett, James
Longman, William, 1813 - 1877)
Lord, Caroline Annie (Ley), (1847 - )
McLaren, Agnes
McLaren, Donnan, (1800 - 1886)
Martin, Louis
Matthew, Patrick
Mazzini, Guiseppe, (1805 - 1872)
Mill, Harriet (Hardy) Taylor, (1807 - 1858)
Mill, John Stuart, (1806 - 1813)
Morley, John, Viscount, (1838 - 1923)
National Association for the Promotion of Social Science
Paterson, John
Pascal, Eugene
Peirce, Charles Saunders, (1839 - 1911)
Phin, John
Political Economy Club, London
Roebuck, John Arthur (1801 - 1879)
Ruge, Arnold, (1802 - 1880)
Rusden, H. K.
Salisbury, Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne Cecil, Third Marquess of, (1830 - 1880)
Schaeffer, J.
Shirreff, Emily Anne Eliza, (lR14 - 1897)
Smith, Goldwin, (1823 - 1910)
Spencer, Herbert, (1820- 1903)
Sterling, John, (1806 - I844)
Taine, Hippolyte Adolphe, (1828 - 1893)
Tauchnitz, Christian Bernhard von, (1816 - 1895)
Taylor, Helen, (1831 - 1907)
Taylor, Helen B.
Taylor, R.
Taylor, Sarah
Thornton, William Thomas, (1813 - 1880)
Trask, James
Trubner &Co.
Venturi, Emilie (Ashurst) Hawkes, ( - 1893)
Villari, Pasquale, (183h - 1917)
White, Horace, (1834 - 1916)
Youmans, Edward Livingston, (182 1 - 1887)
Philosophy; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; England -- Description and travel; Europe; Philosophers; Bentham, Jeremy, 1748-1832; Chadwick, Edwin, 1800-1890; Chapman, John, 1822-1894; Christie, William Dougal, 1816-1874; Cole, Henry, 1808-1882; De Morgan, Augustus, 1806-1871; Dilke, Charles Wentworth, Sir, 1843-1911; Grote, George, 1794-1871; Hardy, Arthur; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), 1792-1871; Hooker, Isabella Beecher, 1822-1907; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Mill, Harriet Hardy Taylor, 1807-1858; Mill, John Stuart, 1806-1873; Morley, John, 1838-1923; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903; Sterling, John, 1806-1844; Taine, Hippolyte, 1828-1893; Tauchnitz, Bernhard, 1816-1895
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1812-1858 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1888, undated (Box 2)
  - Account of a Walking Tour through Berkshire, Buckinghamshire & Surrey, 1828 (Box 2)
  - Photostatic copies of correspondence (Box 3–4)
  - Draft letters to
    - Dr. John Chapman, 1851 June 9 (Box 5)
    - Judge Henry Samuel? Chapman, 1858 July 8 (Box 5)
    - Dr. Walter Coulson, 1850 November 22 (Box 5)
    - Professor C. D. H. Rau, 1852 Nar 20 (Box 5)
    - Professor Green, 1852 April 8 (Box 5)
    - Lord Hobart, 1853? August 7 (Box 5)
    - The Secretary, National Sunday League., 1856 November 3 (Box 5)
    - The author of "Currency Self-Regulating & Elastic." Longmans, 1856 November 26 (Box 5)
    - F. Sinnett, 1857 October 22 (Box 5)
    - The Educational Franchise, 1857 December 11 (Box 5)
    - Wm. Newmarch Esq., 1858 March 20 (Box 5)
    - J. Britten, 1858 July 1 (Box 5)
  - Draft letters to
    - J. J. Louis Blanc, 1858 July 9 (Box 5)
    - Constantine Baer, 1856 December 13 (Box 5)
    - Dr. Adolph Soetbaer, 1852 March 18 (Box 5)